Hello, and welcome to Lesson 12 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好，欢迎来到Wolfram U的微积分入门课程第12课。
The topic of this lesson is implicit differentiation.
本课的主题是隐函数求导。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the topic. So far, all of the functions that we have considered
首先，我们先对该主题做一个简单的概述。到目前为止，我们所接触的所有函数都是
are in so-called explicit form. For example, here is a function f which is defined to be x^2 – x + 1.
是所谓的显式函数。例如，这里有一个函数f，它被定义为x^2 - x+1。
Every time I give you a value of x, you could work out the value of f at that x.
给定一个x的值时，你都可以计算出f在该点x的函数值。
That’s an explicit function, but sometimes you have a function that’s defined only implicitly.
这就是一个显式函数，但有时，你会遇到隐式定义的函数。
For example, here’s an equation x^2 + y^2 = 4, and surely y is a function of x—it depends on x—
例如，方程x^2+y^2=4，显然，y是x的函数 y值取决于x值
but it does so in an indirect implicit way. Now of course in this case, you could solve the equation
可见，函数是以一种隐式的方式表达 当然在这种情况下，你可以求解方程
and work out y in terms of x and you get back two solutions, so really, you have two functions of x,
得到y关于x的解 求解这个方程 会得到两个解 因此 实际会得到两个关于x的函数。
and then you could plot them. What you see is that you have a circle,
然后 绘制函数图像 得到的是一个圆
and the first solution is the bottom of the circle and the second solution is the top half,
方程的第一个解对应圆的下半部分 第二个解则对应上半部分
so that’s of course why you need two functions rather than one to describe the problem.
这也是为什么需要使用两个函数而不是一个函数作为问题的解
That’s solution of an implicit function, and today what we will do is to talk about
这是隐函数求导的一种解决方法 这节课我们要讨论的是
how you can find derivatives implicitly in the Wolfram Language.
如何使用Wolfram语言求解隐函数的导数
Let’s try and do this in one way. For example, you could take the two functions from the earlier page, from the earlier slide,
让我们尝试使用一种方法进行求解 例如 你可以借助前面幻灯片中的两个函数
and try to work out their derivatives separately.
分别计算它们的导数
You get back two answers. Now notice that each answer is of the form minus x or y—
会得到两个导函数 请留意 两个导函数都可以表示为-x/y的形式
so that’s x, that’s y and both answers have a certain pattern to them.
那是x 那是y 可见两个导函数存在一定规律
But then what we’ve got to remember is that this over here is the kind of upper branch,
我们需要记住的是 这部分是图像的上半部分
so the derivative for the upper branch comes from here. If you plug in, let’s say, √2 and √2 that point,
因此 上半部分的导函数来源于这里 例如 你选择(√2, √2)这个点
then what you get back is a slope of −1 at x = √2 for the upper branch.
可以得到上半部分在x=√2处的斜率为-1
You can then plot the line, the tangent line, and the circle, and you see that
可以画出过该点指定斜率的直线、该点切线以及圆 可以发现
that’s the correct solution. But of course this is a very roundabout way of doing things,
这种做法是可行的 但方法十分繁琐
and what we want to do today is to try and do things in a much more clear-cut, simple way,
而这节课要尝试的是一种更清晰、简单的解决方法
and that’s the notion of implicit differentiation. The idea is very simple.
以上是隐函数求导的概念 非常容易理解
Whenever you find the derivative with respect to x, you work just as before;
当遇到求解关于x的导函数的问题时 求解方法如同往常一样
but if you have a y anywhere in your expression, then you also make sure to multiply by dy/dx.
但如果表达式中存在y 那么请确保乘上dy/dx。
For example, here’s the equation from the earlier slide and you have x^2 + y^2 = 4,
举例说明 这是来自前面幻灯片的方程 方程x^2 + y^2 = 4。
so the derivative of x^2 is 2x, and the derivative of y^2 is not just 2y, but 2y times dy/dx.
x^2的导数是2x，y^2的导数是不仅仅是2y，而是2y再乘以dy/dx。
That’s just the chain rule. Okay. Once we have done that, then from the equation
这里用到了链式法则 完成了这一步 那么从等式上看
you can solve for dy/dx and find the answer is negative x or y, just as we noted earlier.
可以解出dy/dx 答案是-x/y 与前面提到的一致
That’s the technique for doing implicit differentiation, and now I’ll show you how we can do it in the Wolfram Language.
这就是隐函数求导的方法 下面给大家演示一下 我们如何在Wolfram语言中完成这一任务
Let’s take up the circle again. There are two ways to go about it.
我们再次选择这个圆 完成求解有两种方法
In the first method, what you do is you replace y by y[x]. Now the Wolfram Language knows that y is
第一种方法 你需要将y替换成y[x] Wolfram语言就能知道y是
indeed a function of x, and then you tell D to find the derivative. Then you solve that derivative for y'[x].
关于x的函数 之后再调用D求导 最终解得导函数y'[x]
What you get back is exactly what we guessed earlier on—namely, negative x or y.
得到的结果正是我们之前的猜测 即-x/y
Okay. Now we can plug in values for both x and y. For example, if you’re at the point (−1, √3)
好 我们现在可以选择x和y值进行代入 例如 在(-1, √3)这个点的
where the slope is 1/√3, and you can then find a tangent and plot both the tangent and the graph,
斜率为1/√3 可以绘制该点的切线 并将切线和图形绘制出来
and you see that the answer is correct. That’s the first method. The first method is replace y by y[x].
你会发现 答案是正确的 以上就是第一种方法 第一种方法是将y替换为y[x]
The second method is slightly different. You start with the equation, but now do not make a replacement.
第二种方法略有不同 首先输入方程 但不进行替换
Instead, you tell D that y is no longer a constant, and that’s done with the NonConstants option.
之后 调用D 使用NonConstants参数说明y不是常数
When you do that, you get back an equation for D. You solve it and you get back
当你完成以上步骤 会得到一个含有D的方程 将其求解 会得到
just the same derivative as before, but now you only have a y instead of y[x].
与前面相同的导数 但现在的答案中包含y而不是y[x]。
So there are two ways: replace y[x] or use the NonConstants option. Usually we’ll work with the first way.
综上 有两种方法 替换为y[x]或使用NonConstants参数 通常我们会采用第一种方法
That’s a little more natural, but there will be another case where we’ll actually try and use the second method,
方法一比较自然 当然 我们也可以尝试使用第二种方法
but that will be in the exercises for the lesson.
这将会在本课练习中出现
Okay. Having done this preparatory work, we can now find lots of derivatives with this method.
好 完成了这些预备工作 我们现在可以使用这个方法求解许多的导函数了
For example, here is a famous curve called the Folium of Descartes. That’s the equation of the curve.
例如 这是著名的笛卡儿叶形线的曲线方程
We want to find the derivative, so you replace y by y[x], work out the derivative, solve for it like over here
我们想要求它的导数 因此你将y都替换成y[x] 像这里一样求解出导数
and replace x and y with the values that you want to work with, 2 and 2,
并根据所需的点(2,2) 替换x和y的值
and you get back the derivative of this curve at (2, 2). Work out the tangent line,
可以得到这条曲线在（2，2）处的导数 再求出切线方程
and then you plot the curve and the tangent, and it looks just right.
之后 绘制曲线和切线 结果看起来十分正确
As another example, let’s take up the ellipse. That’s like a distorted circle,
另一个例子 让我们来看看椭圆 就像是一个扭曲的圆
and you want to find the tangent line at the point (1, (−√3/2)). Again, you do the same thing:
你想求出在点（1，（-√3/2））处的切线 又一次 你要做相同的工作
replace y with y[x], solve the equation, plug in the values, get back the slope, set up the equation for tangent
将y替换为y[x] 解方程 代入值 得到斜率 求出切线方程
and you get back the plot of the ellipse with the tangent line. Okay.
可以得到椭圆与切线的图 结果正确 好
From the ellipse, we go on to the hyperbola. That’s the hyperbola equation. You want to work
从椭圆出发 接下来是双曲线 这是双曲线的方程 你想求出
at a certain point that’s given to you. Again, replace y with y[x], solve for y'[x],
给定点的切线斜率 又一次 将y换成y[x] 解得y'[x]
plug in the values and you get back the slope. Write down the equation for tangent,
再代入点的坐标 就可以得到切线斜率 与切线方程
and then you plot the tangent and the curve, and you get back this nice picture.
然后画出切线和曲线 就得到了这张好看的曲线
Notice that in all these plots, I’m using the ContourPlot function to plot the curve itself
请注意 在这些图中 都使用了ContourPlot函数来绘制曲线本身
while using the Plot function to plot the tangent line.
而使用Plot函数绘制切线
Okay. My next example is the so-called cardioid. That’s like a heart-shaped curve,
好 下一个例子是所谓的心形 像一个心形曲线
which is a pretty difficult equation. Here’s the equation of the curve. Replace y with y[x] as before,
这是一个相当复杂的方程 这里给出了曲线的方程 如前 将y替换为y[x]
find the derivative. It’s 1. Write our tangent equation, and then you plot the tangent of the curve,
求出导数 结果是1 写出切线方程 绘制曲线切线
and you get back this beautiful plot of the cardioid.
会得到这个美丽的心形图像
Another example is the so-called devil’s curve.
又例如 这个所谓的魔鬼曲线
Now it doesn’t matter how difficult or easy the equation looks. You do just the same thing.
无论方程看起来有多么复杂或简单 你也做相同的步骤
You take the equation, replace y with y[x] everywhere. You’ve just seen it before,
将方程中的y替换为y[x] 正如刚才演示的
so now I’ll plug in the correct x and y values, and when you do that, you get back the slope.
然后 代入所需的x和y值 完成这一步 就得到了斜率
Write down the equation for tangent, so that’s the y1, if you like, from your work on straight lines;
将切线方程写下来 这一项是切点的纵坐标y1
that’s the slope; and that’s x − x1. Okay. You plot the tangent and the curve.
这一项是斜率 这一项就是x-x1（x1为切点横坐标） 好的 再画出切线和曲线。
Notice one thing: the tangent line at this point might actually pass the curve again
请注意 这种情况下的切线会再次通过曲线
because the curve in this case is like a loop attached to the location.
原因是 这种情况下 曲线就像连接到特定位置的环
Okay. Another example is the so-called kampyle of Eudoxus. That’s the equation,
好吧 还有一个例子就是杖头线 方程如下
but just the same method works: replace y by y[x], solve, replace values and you get back the slope.
使用同样的方法：将y替换为y[x] 求解 代入 可以得到斜率
That’s the tangent line over here, and then you plot the tangent line and the curve,
这是切线方程 把切线和曲线画出来
and you get back the correct solution.
得到正确的解答
Having talked about derivatives, let’s now spend just a few minutes talking about multiple derivatives.
讨论完了导数 接下来花几分钟谈谈高阶导数
Here’s an equation. You want to work out not just the first derivative, but also the second derivative with implicit differentiation.
给定方程 不仅要求出隐函数的一阶导数 还要求出二阶导数
You write the equation down. Replace y by y[x],
方程中 使用y[x]来代替y。
solve and find the derivative. Then you find the second derivative by putting the two over here for the second derivatives,
求解并得到导数 为求解二阶导数 将参数2放到这个位置
and you get back the second derivative.
就能得到二阶导数
Unfortunately, the second derivative has the first derivative in it, but then you can use
不幸的是，二阶导数的表达式中含有一阶导数 不过 你可以使用
the earlier step to plug in values. You plug in the first solution into the second one,
前面代入数值的步骤 将一阶导数代入二阶导数中
and you get back the second derivative now in a much simpler form
就能得到形式简洁很多的二阶导数
where it depends only on x and y.
只取决于x和y。
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson.
好的 到此为止 这节课接近尾声
Basically, there are two ways to compute the derivatives of implicit functions. In the first one, we express, let’s say,
总结来说 有两种方法来计算隐函数的导数 第一种方法 我们将
y as a function of x. In the second one, we could use the NonConstants option.
y表示为x的函数 第二种方法 我们可以使用NonConstants参数
Now both methods have got their advantages and disadvantages, but overall,
这两种方法各有优缺点 但总体来说
the first method is much closer to what you do by hand, and I recommend that you follow the first method.
第一种方法更接近手工操作 我个人建议采用第一种方法
Of course we saw lots of interesting curves, and you could plot them
这节课我们还看到了很多有趣的曲线 你可以将它们绘制出来
and then actually work out the derivatives, and ContourPlot is a really good function for plotting these curves.
计算出导数 此外 ContourPlot是一个用于绘制曲线 非常好用的函数
That’s the end of this lesson. The next lesson will talk about rates of change,
这节课到此结束 下一节课将讲变化率
but before doing that, you should definitely review today’s lesson, try lots of examples
在下一节课前 你要先复习今天的课程 尝试大量的例子
and make yourself ready for the next lesson. Of course, we’ll also have a problem session before we go onto the next lesson.
为下节课做好准备 当然 我们还设置了习题的环节
Thank you very much.
非常感谢大家！
I hope you’ve enjoyed the lesson. I’ll stop there.
我希望你能喜欢这节课 这节课到此结束